Where does the end begin?
أين تبدأ النهاية؟
Well, for me, it all began with this little fellow.
حسناً، بالنسبة لي، بدأ كل شيء مع هذا الرفيق الصغير.
This adorable organism --
هذا الكائن الحي اللطيف...
well, I think it's adorable --
أعتقد أنه لطيف...
is called Tetrahymena and it's a single-celled creature.
يسمى رباعية الغشاء وهو مخلوق وحيد الخلية.
It's also been known as pond scum.
وهو معروف أيضا باسم زبد البرك.
So that's right, my career started with pond scum.
فهذا صحيح، بدأت حياتي المهنية بزبد البرك.
Now, it was no surprise I became a scientist.
ليس بالأمر المفاجئ أن أصبح عالمة.
Growing up far away from here,
في فترة نشأتي بعيدًا عن هنا،
as a little girl I was deadly curious
كنت فضولية بجنون كفتاة صغيرة
about everything alive.
عن كل ما هو حي.
I used to pick up lethally poisonous stinging jellyfish and sing to them.
اعتدت التقاط القناديل اللاسعة ذات السم القاتل والغناء لهم.
And so starting my career,
في بداية مساري المهني،
I was deadly curious about fundamental mysteries
كنت شديدة الفضول عن الأسرار الأساسية
of the most basic building blocks of life,
عن أهم اللبنات الأساسية للحياة،
and I was fortunate to live in a society where that curiosity was valued.
وكنت محظوظة أن عشت في مجتمع يقدر هذا الفضول.
Now, for me, this little pond scum critter Tetrahymena
حسنًا، بالنسبة لي، رباعية الغشاء، زبد البرك هذه
was a great way to study the fundamental mystery
كان طريقة رائعة لدراسة السر الأساسي،
I was most curious about:
كنت أكثر فضولاً حول:
those bundles of DNA in our cells called chromosomes.
هذه الحزم من الأحماض النووية في خلايانا التي تسمى بالكروموسومات.
And it was because I was curious about the very ends of chromosomes,
خصوصاً نهايات الكروموسومات،
known as telomeres.
التي تعرف بالتيلوميرات.
Now, when I started my quest,
حسنًا، عندما بدأت بحثي،
all we knew was that they helped protect the ends of chromosomes.
كان كل ما نعرفه عن التيلوميرات هو أنهم يحمون نهايات الكروموسومات.
It was important when cells divide.
وأهميتهم عند انقسام الخلايا.
It was really important,
فلهم دور في غاية الأهمية،
but I wanted to find out what telomeres consisted of,
لكني أردت معرفة ما تتكون منه التيلوميرات،
and for that, I needed a lot of them.
لذلك، كنت في حاجة للكثير منهم.
And it so happens that cute little Tetrahymena
ويتصادف أن رباعية الغشاء الصغير اللطيف
has a lot of short linear chromosomes,
لديه الكثير من الكروموسومات الخطية القصيرة،
around 20,000,
حوالي عشرين ألفًا،
so lots of telomeres.
وهذه تيلوميرات كثيرة.
And I discovered that telomeres consisted of special segments
واكتشفت أن التيلوميرات تتكون من شرائح الخاصة،
of noncoding DNA right at the very ends of chromosomes.
من الأحماض النووية غير مشفرة في نهايات الكروموسومات بالتحديد.
But here's a problem.
ولكن هنا مشكلة.
Now, we all start life as a single cell.
كلنا نبدأ حياتنا بخلية واحدة.
It multiples to two. Two becomes four. Four becomes eight,
ثم تتضاعف الخلية إلى اثنتين، ثم إلى أربعة، ثم إلى ثمانية،
and on and on to form the 200 million billion cells
وهكذا دواليك، لتكوين المئتي مليون مليار خلية،
that make up our adult body.
التي تشكل أجسادنا البالغة.
And some of those cells have to divide thousands of times.
وعلى بعض تلك الخلايا، التضاعف آلاف المرات.
In fact, even as I stand here before you,
في الواقع، بينما أقف هنا أمامكم،
all throughout my body, cells are furiously replenishing
يتم تجديد خلايا جسدي بشراسة،
to, well, keep me standing here before you.
لإبقائي واقفة هنا أمامكم.
So every time a cell divides, all of its DNA has to be copied,
ففي كل مرة تنقسم الخلية، يتم نسخ كلي لحمضها النووي،
all of the coding DNA inside of those chromosomes,
كل الحمض النووي المشفر بداخل هذه الكروموسومات،
because that carries the vital operating instructions
لأنه يحمل تعليمات التشغيل الأساسية،
that keep our cells in good working order,
التي تبقي خلايانا في نظام عمل مستقر،
so my heart cells can keep a steady beat,
حتى تتمكن خلايا قلبي من الحفاظ على معدل ضربات ثابت،
which I assure you they're not doing right now,
وهو معدل أؤكد لكم أنهم لا يحافظون عليه الآن،
and my immune cells
وحتى تتمكن خلاياي المناعية
can fight off bacteria and viruses,
من محاربة البكتيريا والفيروسات،
and our brain cells can save the memory of our first kiss
وتتمكن خلايانا الدماغية من حفظ ذكرى قبلتنا الأولى
and keep on learning throughout life.
والاستمرار في التعلم على طول العمر.
But there is a glitch in the way DNA is copied.
ولكن هناك خلل في طريقة نسخ الحمض النووي.
It is just one of those facts of life.
وهذه حقيقة من حقائق الحياة.
Every time the cell divides and the DNA is copied,
ففي كل مرة تنقسم الخلية، ويُنسخ الحمض النووي الخاص بها،
some of that DNA from the ends gets worn down and shortened,
يتآكل بعض هذا الآخير الذي في النهايات ويقصر طوله،
some of that telomere DNA.
بعض الحمض النووي في التيلوميرات.
And think about it
مثل ما يحدث
like the protective caps at the ends of your shoelace.
للبلاستيك الموجود في نهايات أربطة الأحذية.
And those keep the shoelace, or the chromosome, from fraying,
التي تحافظ على رباط الحذاء، أو الكروموسومات، من الانحلال،
and when that tip gets too short, it falls off,
وعندما تصبح هذه الأطراف قصيرة جداً، تسقط،
and that worn down telomere sends a signal to the cells.
ويرسل هذا التيلومير المتآكل إشارة للخلية.
"The DNA is no longer being protected."
"لم يعد هناك ما يحمي الحمض النووي."
It sends a signal. Time to die.
ويرسل إشارة مفادها: حان وقت الموت.
So, end of story.
وبالتالي، نهاية القصة.
Well, sorry, not so fast.
لكن، ليس بهذه السرعة.
It can't be the end of the story,
لا يمكن أن تكون هذه نهاية القصة،
because life hasn't died off the face of the earth.
لأن الحياة لم تختفِ من على وجه الأرض.
So I was curious:
فأثار فضولي أنه:
if such wear and tear is inevitable,
إذا كان هذا الأمر لا مفر منه،
how on earth does Mother Nature make sure
كيف تتأكد الطبيعة الأم من ذلك،
we can keep our chromosomes intact?
بإبقاء بعض الكروموزومات سليمة؟
Now, remember that little pond scum critter Tetrahymena?
حسنًا، لنعد لرباعية الغشاء
The craziest thing was, Tetrahymena cells never got old and died.
أكثر الأشياء غرابة عند هذا الكائن، أن خلاياه لا تهرم ولا تمت أبدًا
Their telomeres weren't shortening as time marched on.
هذه التيلوميرات لا تقصر بمرور الزمن.
Sometimes they even got longer.
بل إن طولها يزداد أحيانًا.
Something else was at work,
هناك شيء آخر يلعب دورًا،
and believe me, that something was not in any textbook.
شيء غير مذكور في أي مقرر تعليمي.
So working in my lab with my extraordinary student Carol Greider --
في المختبر، عندما كنت أعمل مع إحدى طالباتي (كارول غريدر)
and Carol and I shared the Nobel Prize for this work --
هذا العمل، الذي مكننا من الفوز بجائزة نوبل--
we began running experiments
بدأنا إجراء التجارب
and we discovered cells do have something else.
واكتشفنا أن الخلايا لديها شيء آخر.
It was a previously undreamed-of enzyme
تملك أنزيما لا مثيل له،
that could replenish, make longer, telomeres,
يمكن من بناء وإطالة التيلومترات
and we named it telomerase.
سميناه تيلوميريز.
And when we removed our pond scum's telomerase,
عندما أزلنا تيلوميريز، من التيلومترات تحت التجريب،
their telomeres ran down and they died.
تقلصت هذه الأخيرة وماتت
So it was thanks to their plentiful telomerase
إذن فبفضل غنى تيلوميريز
that our pond scum critters never got old.
لا تشيخ الكائنات البحرية تحت التجريب،
OK, now, that's an incredibly hopeful message
هذه رسالة مليئة بالأمل،
for us humans to be receiving from pond scum,
لنا كبشر، من زبد البرك
because it turns out
لأنه يجب أن نعرف،
that as we humans age, our telomeres do shorten,
نحن كبشر، التيلومترات خاصتنا، تصغر مع مرور الزمن،
and remarkably, that shortening is aging us.
هذا الصغر هو سبب تقدمنا في السن،
Generally speaking, the longer your telomeres,
باختصار، كلما طالت التيلومترات خاصتنا،
the better off you are.
نعيش أفضل،
It's the overshortening of telomeres
عندما تصبح قصيرة،
that leads us to feel and see signs of aging.
نلاحظ علامة الشيخوخة تبدو علينا،
My skin cells start to die
الخلايا الجلدية تموت،
and I start to see fine lines, wrinkles.
بدأت ألاحظ خطوطاً صغيرةً، تجاعيد،
Hair pigment cells die.
تموت خلايا صبغة الشعر.
You start to see gray.
ويبدأ اللون الرمادي في الظهور.
Immune system cells die.
وتموت خلايا النظام المناعي.
You increase your risks of getting sick.
وتزيد فرص إصابتك بالأمراض.
In fact, the cumulative research from the last 20 years
أوضحت البحوث التراكمية في السنوات ال 20 الماضية
has made clear that telomere attrition
أن استنزاف التيلوميرات
is contributing to our risks of getting cardiovascular diseases,
يزيد من احتمالية إصابتنا بأمراض القلب والأوعية الدموية،
Alzheimer's, some cancers and diabetes,
والزهايمر، وبعض السرطانات والسكري،
the very conditions many of us die of.
الحالات التي تقتل العديد منا.
And so we have to think about this.
فعلينا بالتالي التفكير بذلك.
What is going on?
ما الذي يجري؟
This attrition,
مع هذا الاستنزاف،
we look and we feel older, yeah.
نبدو و نحس أننا أكبر في السن،
Our telomeres are losing the war of attrition faster.
التيلومترات خاصتنا، تفقد الحرب ضد هذا الاستنزاف بسرعة
And those of us who feel youthful longer,
بالنسبة لأولئك الذين يحسون أكثر شباباً، لوقت أطول
it turns out our telomeres are staying longer
يعني أن التيلومترات خاصتهم، حافضت على طولها
for longer periods of time,
لمدة أطول،
extending our feelings of youthfulness
وبالتالي تطيل فترة شبابهم،
and reducing the risks of all we most dread
وتحد من مخاطر كل ما نخشاه
as the birthdays go by.
مع مرور السنوات،
OK,
حسنًا،
seems like a no-brainer.
يبدو هذا سهلاً،
Now, if my telomeres are connected
حسنًأ، إذا كانت تيلوميراتي مرتبطة
to how quickly I'm going to feel and get old,
بسرعة شيخوختي،
if my telomeres can be renewed by my telomerase,
إذا كان يمكن تجديد التيلومترات خاصتي، بفضل التيلوميراز
then all I have to do to reverse the signs and symptoms of aging
فكل ما عليك القيام به لعكس علامات وأعراض التقدم في السن،
is figure out where to buy that Costco-sized bottle
هو الحصول على زجاجة كبيرة الحجم
of grade A organic fair trade telomerase, right?
من التيلوميراز عالية الجودة، أليس كذالك؟
Great! Problem solved.
عظيم! حُلّت المشكلة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Not so fast, I'm sorry.
ليس بهذه السرعة للأسف.
Alas, that's not the case.
لا يمكن فعل هذا.
OK. And why?
حسنًا. لماذا؟
It's because human genetics has taught us
لأن علم الوراثة البشرية علّمنا
that when it comes to our telomerase,
أنه عندما يتعلق الأمر بالتيلوميراز خاصتنا،
we humans live on a knife edge.
نحن البشر على حافة سكين.
OK, simply put,
حسنًا ، ببساطة ،
yes, nudging up telomerase does decrease the risks of some diseases,
نعم ، فالتيلوميراز المعدل يقلل من مخاطر بعض الأمراض ،
but it also increases the risks of certain and rather nasty cancers.
لكنه يزيد أيضًا من مخاطر الإصابة ببعض أنواع السرطان.
So even if you could buy that Costco-sized bottle of telomerase,
لذلك حتى لو كان بإمكانك شراء زجاجة تيلوميراز كبيرة
and there are many websites marketing such dubious products,
وهناك العديد من المواقع تسوق هذه المنتجات المشكوك فيها ،
the problem is you could nudge up your risks of cancers.
المشكل هو أنك تزيد من مخاطر الإصابة بالسرطان.
And we don't want that.
ونحن لا نريد ذلك.
Now, don't worry,
حسنًا، لا تقلقوا،
and because, while I think it's kind of funny that right now,
يجب أن أعترف لكم بأنني أجد ذلك مضحكا، لأنني أعتقد الآن
you know, many of us may be thinking, "Well, I'd rather be like pond scum," ...
أن معظمنا يفضل أن يصبح ككائنات البرك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
there is something for us humans
هنا درس لنا كبشر
in the story of telomeres and their maintenance.
في حياة التيلوميرات وصيانتها.
But I want to get one thing clear.
أريد إيضاحه.
It isn't about enormously extending human lifespan
ليس المهم أن نزيد في حياة البشر ..
or immortality.
أو أن نصل للخلود.
It's about health span.
بل المهم هو الصحة
Now, health span is the number of years of your life
حسنًا،EVSI هي عدد السنين التي نعيشها
when you're free of disease, you're healthy, you're productive,
وأنت سليم دون مرض
you're zestfully enjoying life.
تتمتع بحياتك،
Disease span, the opposite of health span,
على العكس، أمل الحياة في حالة المرض،
is the time of your life spent feeling old and sick and dying.
هو الوقت الذي نقضيه في الشعور بالمرض، كبر السن والموت.
So the real question becomes,
ثم تنشأ المشكلة الحقيقية.
OK, if I can't guzzle telomerase,
لا يمكننا امتصاص التيلوميراز ،
do I have control over my telomeres' length
لكن يمكننا التحكم في طولها،
and hence my well-being, my health,
وبالتالي نحسن من صحتنا ومستوى معيشتنا
without those downsides of cancer risks?
والتقليل من خطر إصابتنا بالسرطان،
OK?
أليس كذالك؟
So, it's the year 2000.
لنعد لسنة 2000،
Now, I've been minutely scrutinizing little teeny tiny telomeres
في ذلك الوقت، بدأت دراسة التيلوميرات الصغيرة جدا
very happily for many years,
منذ سنوات،
when into my lab walks a psychologist named Elissa Epel.
عندما دخلت طبيبة نفسية تدعى إليسا إبيل مختبري.
Now, Elissa's expertise is in the effects of severe, chronic psychological stress
إليسا اختصاصية الضغط النفسي المزمن
on our mind's and our body's health.
على صحة عقولنا وأجسامنا .
And there she was standing in my lab,
وهناك كانت تقف في مختبري،
which ironically overlooked the entrance to a mortuary, and --
من سخرية القدر أطلت على مدخل المشرحة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And she had a life-and-death question for me.
سألتني سؤالاً بمثابة مسألة حياة أو موت بالنسبة لي.
"What happens to telomeres in people who are chronically stressed?"
"ماذا يحدث للتيلوميرات عند الناس الذين يعانون من الأرق المزمن؟"
she asked me.
سألتني.
You see, she'd been studying caregivers,
قالت أنها قامت بدراسة عن مقدمي الرعاية،
and specifically mothers of children with a chronic condition,
وعلى وجه التحديد أمهات الأطفال الذين يعانون من أمراض مزمنة،
be it gut disorder, be it autism, you name it --
مثل أمراض الجهاز الهضمي، التوحد، أو مرض آخر -
a group obviously under enormous and prolonged psychological stress.
المجموعة المختارة كانت تحت ضغط نفسي شديد ودائم.
I have to say, her question
ولا بد من الاعتراف أن
changed me profoundly.
سؤالها غيرني بشكل كبير.
See, all this time I had been thinking of telomeres
طول هذا الوقت كنت أفكر في التيلوميرات
as those miniscule molecular structures that they are,
مثل تلك الهياكل الجزيئية الصغيرة،
and the genes that control telomeres.
والجينات التي تتحكم في التيلوميرات.
And when Elissa asked me about studying caregivers,
سؤال إليسا لي حول مقدمي الرعاية،
I suddenly saw telomeres in a whole new light.
غير رأيي حول التيلوميرات.
I saw beyond the genes and the chromosomes
أصبحت أرى أبعد من الجينات والكروموسومات
into the lives of the real people we were studying.
آخد بعين الاعتبار حياة الناس الذين تتم إجراء الدراسة عليهم.
And I'm a mom myself,
حتى أنا لدي أطفال،
and at that moment,
وفي تلك اللحظة،
I was struck by the image of these women
أدهشتني صورة هؤلاء النساء،
dealing with a child with a condition
اللواتي يرعين الأطفال المرضى،
very difficult to deal with, often without help.
فمن الصعب التعامل معهم من دون مساعدة.
And such women, simply,
وهؤلاء النساء،
often look worn down.
اللواتي أرهقهن الزمن.
So was it possible their telomeres were worn down as well?
بالتالي فالتيلوميرات خاصتهم، ألن تكون كذالك مرهقة؟
So our collective curiosity went into overdrive.
هكذا انبثق فضولنا الجماعي.
Elissa selected for our first study a group of such caregiving mothers,
في دراستنا الأولى، قامت إليسا بتكوين أول مجموعة أمهات راعيات،
and we wanted to ask: What's the length of their telomeres
أردنا أن نعرف: ما هو طول التيلوميرات خاصتهم؟
compared with the number of years that they have been caregiving
هل يتناسب مع عدد السنوات التي كن يقدمن الرعاية فيها
for their child with a chronic condition?
لأطفالهم في حالة مرض مزمن؟
So four years go by
بعد أربع سنوات
and the day comes when all the results are in,
واليوم تأتي النتائج،
and Elissa looked down at our first scatterplot
نظرت إليسا إلى المخطط الأول
and literally gasped,
وهتفت متسائلةً
because there was a pattern to the data,
أنه كان هناك تطور تم الكشف عنه.
and it was the exact gradient that we most feared might exist.
وهو ما كنا نخشاه،
It was right there on the page.
تم تدوينه بوضوح.
The longer, the more years that is,
كلما زاد عدد السنوات،
the mother had been in this caregiving situation,
التي تقدم فيها أم الرعاية لابنها،
no matter her age,
بغض النظر عن سنها،
the shorter were her telomeres.
كلما قصُرت التيلوميرات خاصتها.
And the more she perceived
وكلما اعتبرت الأم
her situation as being more stressful,
حالتها على أنها أكثر إرهاقا،
the lower was her telomerase and the shorter were her telomeres.
كلما قصُرت التيلوميرات خاصتها.
So we had discovered something unheard of:
اكتشفنا شيئًا جديدًا:
the more chronic stress you are under, the shorter your telomeres,
كلما زاد الإجهاد المزمن عند شخص، كلما قصرت التيلوميرات الخاصة به،
meaning the more likely you were to fall victim to an early disease span
هذا يعني قصر أمل الحياة،
and perhaps untimely death.
وربما الوفاة المبكرة.
Our findings meant that people's life events
النتائج التي توصلنا إليها تبين أن ما نعيشه
and the way we respond to these events
والطريقة التي نتصرف بها حيال هذه الأحداث
can change how you maintain your telomeres.
تؤثر على التيلوميرات الخاصة بنا.
So telomere length wasn't just a matter of age counted in years.
لذلك فطول التيلوميرات لا يتعلق بالعمر فقط.
Elissa's question to me,
السؤال الذي طرحته إليسا،
back when she first came to my lab, indeed had been a life-and-death question.
كان بالفعل مسألة حياة أو موت.
Now, luckily, hidden in that data there was hope.
لحسن الحظ، كان هناك أمل في تلك البيانات .
We noticed that some mothers,
لاحظنا أن بعض الأمهات،
despite having been carefully caring for their children for many years,
رغم اهتمامهم بأبنائهم لسنوات عديدة،
had been able to maintain their telomeres.
فالتيلوميرات الخاصة بهن بقيت كما هي.
So studying these women closely revealed that they were resilient to stress.
بدراستنا لهؤلاء النسوة عن كثب، اكشفنا أنهن مقاومات للأرق.
Somehow they were able to experience their circumstances
كن قادرات على مواجهة ظروفهن،
not as a threat day in and day out
لا يعتبرنه كتهديد ،
but as a challenge,
وإنما بمثابة تحد،
and this has led to a very important insight for all of us:
هذا يقودنا إلى فكرة مهمة جدا بالنسبة لنا جميعا
we have control over the way we age
أن لدينا سيطرة على طريقة تقدمنا ​​في العمر
all the way down into our cells.
إلى غاية خلايانا.
OK, now our initial curiosity became infectious.
الآن ذلك الفضول الأولي انتشر بيننا كالعدوى.
Thousands of scientists from different fields
الآلاف من العلماء من مختلف المجالات
added their expertise to telomere research,
يفيدون بخبراتهم فيما يخص أبحاث التيلومير،
and the findings have poured in.
وحصلنا على نتائج متنوعة.
It's up to over 10,000 scientific papers and counting.
نحن الآن أمام 10.000 مقالة علمية،
So several studies rapidly confirmed our initial finding
والعديد من الدراسات أثبتت أول اكتشاف لنا
that yes, chronic stress is bad for telomeres.
أن الإجهاد المزمن هو عدو التيلوميرات.
And now many are revealing
والعديد من الدراسات أكدت
that we have more control over this particular aging process
أن لدينا المزيد من السيطرة على تقدمنا في السن
than any of us could ever have imagined.
أكثر مما نتصور.
A few examples:
بعض الأمثلة:
a study from the University of California, Los Angeles
دراسة من جامعة كاليفورنيا في لوس أنجلوس
of people who are caring for a relative with dementia, long-term,
عن الناس الذين يرعون أحد الأقارب الذي يعاني من الخرف، على المدى الطويل،
and looked at their caregiver's telomere maintenance capacity
ونظرت إلى قدرة صيانة تيلوميرات الرعاية الخاصة بهم
and found that it was improved
ووجدت أنها تحسنت،
by them practicing a form of meditation
بممارستهم أحد أشكال التأمل
for as little as 12 minutes a day for two months.
ما يقارب 12 دقيقة يوميا لمدة شهرين.
Attitude matters.
عاداتنا لها دور.
If you're habitually a negative thinker,
إذا كان شخص ذو تفكير سلبي،
you typically see a stressful situation with a threat stress response,
يعيش كل حالة مؤرقة كتهديد،
meaning if your boss wants to see you,
يعني إذا طلب رئيسه في العمل أن يراه،
you automatically think, "I'm about to be fired,"
يقول، "سيتم فصلي عن العمل"
and your blood vessels constrict,
يتعرض لارتفاع ضغط الدم،
and your level of the stress hormone cortisol creeps up,
يرتفع مستوى هرمون الإجهاد الكورتيزول،
and then it stays up,
دون أن ينخفظ،
and over time, that persistently high level of the cortisol
مع الوقت، استمرار ارتفاع حجم الكورتيزول
actually damps down your telomerase.
يكون له وقع سلبي على التيلوميراز خاصتنا
Not good for your telomeres.
وبالتالي على التيلوميرات الخاصة بنا.
On the other hand,
من ناحية أخرى،
if you typically see something stressful as a challenge to be tackled,
إذا كنت ترى حالة ما مرهقة بمثابة تحدي،
then blood flows to your heart and to your brain,
فإن الدم يتدفق إلى قلبك وعقلك، بطريقة طبيعية،
and you experience a brief but energizing spike of cortisol.
ولا يحس إلا بحقنة كورتيزول صغيرة منشطة.
And thanks to that habitual "bring it on" attitude,
وبفضل التعامل مع المواقف "ببرودة" ،
your telomeres do just fine.
ستكون التيلوميرات خاصتنا على ما يرام.
So ...
وبالتالي ...
What is all of this telling us?
ماذا يعني هاذا؟
Your telomeres do just fine.
التيلوميرات خاصتنا ستكون على ما يرام.
You really do have power to change what is happening
هل حقا لدينا القدرة على تغيير ما يحدث
to your own telomeres.
بالنسبة للتيلوميرات خاصتنا.
But our curiosity just got more and more intense,
ازداد فضولنا،
because we started to wonder,
وبدأنا نتساءل،
what about factors outside our own skin?
ماذا عن العوامل خارج جسمنا؟
Could they impact our telomere maintenance as well?
هل يمكن أن تؤثر صيانة التيلوميرات خاصتنا؟
You know, we humans are intensely social beings.
كما تعلمون، نحن البشر كائنات اجتماعية بطبعنا.
Was it even possible that our telomeres were social as well?
هل من الممكن أن تكون التيلوميرات خاصتنا اجتماعية كذلك؟
And the results have been startling.
وكانت النتائج مذهلة.
As early as childhood,
في وقت مبكر من الطفولة،
emotional neglect, exposure to violence,
الإهمال العاطفي، والتعرض للعنف،
bullying and racism
البلطجة والمضايقات
all impact your telomeres, and the effects are long-term.
لها تأثير على التيلوميرات، نحس به على المدى الطويل،
Can you imagine the impact on children
يمكنك أن تتخيل تأثير ذلك على الأطفال
of living years in a war zone?
الذين عاشوا لفترة طويلة في منطقة حرب
People who can't trust their neighbors
الأشخاص الذين لا يثيقون
and who don't feel safe in their neighborhoods
في أقاربهم، ولا يحسون بالأمان في محيطهم
consistently have shorter telomeres.
يملكون تيلوميرات أقصر،
So your home address matters for telomeres as well.
إذن فمكان عيشنا يؤثر على التيلوميرات خاصتنا،
On the flip side,
على العكس،
tight-knit communities, being in a marriage long-term,
في المجتمعات المتجانسة، يدوم الزواج لفترات أطول
and lifelong friendships, even,
نفس الأمر بالنسبة للصدقات،
all improve telomere maintenance.
ما يقوي صيانة التيلوميرات خاصتنا،
So what is all this telling us?
ماذا يعني كل هذا؟
It's telling us that I have the power to impact my own telomeres,
يعني أن لدينا قدرة للتأثير على التيلوميرات الخاصة بنا ،
and I also have the power to impact yours.
وتيلوميرات الآخرين .
Telomere science has told us just how interconnected we all are.
لقد أخبرنا علم التيلومير عن مدى الترابط بيننا.
But I'm still curious.
لكن لا زلت فضولية.
I do wonder
أتساءل
what legacy all of us
ما الإرث الذي سنتركه للأجيال القادمة؟
Will we invest
هل سنستثمر في المرأة أو الرجل القادم
peering through a microscope at the next little critter,
الذي سينحني على الميكروسكوب لاكتشاف كائن جديد
the next bit of pond scum,
كائن برك جديد.
curious about a question we don't even know today is a question?
سيهتم بمشكل لم يظهر بعد.
It could be a great question that could impact all the world.
مشكل يمكن أن يكون على الصعيد العالمي
And maybe, maybe you're curious about you.
ممكن الآن أن يصيبكم الفضول عن أنفسكم،
Now that you know how to protect your telomeres,
تعرفون الآن كيف تحمون التيلوميرات خاصتكم
are you curious what are you going to do
ماذا ستفعلون الآن؟
with all those decades of brimming good health?
مع كل هذه العقود من الصحة الجيدة؟
And now that you know you could impact the telomeres of others,
الآن بعد أن علمتم أن بإمكانكم التأثير على تيلوميرات الآخرين،
are you curious
هل تتساءلون؟
how will you make a difference?
كيف لكم أن تحدثوا فرقا؟
And now that you know the power of curiosity to change the world,
والآن بعد أن تعرفتم على قوة الفضول في تغيير العالم،
how will you make sure that the world invests in curiosity
كيف يمكنكم التأكد من أن العالم يستثمر في الفضول
for the sake of the generations that will come after us?
من أجل الأجيال التي ستأتي بعدنا؟
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)